<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The false--teacher tried and cast. A subject useful at all times, and but too seasonable for the present. / By John Brinsley minister of the gospel at Great Yarmouth.</title>
            <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1821_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868637</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868637</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170416</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170416)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 227:E1821[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The false--teacher tried and cast. A subject useful at all times, and but too seasonable for the present. / By John Brinsley minister of the gospel at Great Yarmouth.</title>
                  <author>Brinsley, John, 1600-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.T. for Thomas Newberry, in Cornhil neer to the Royal Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Clergy --  Office --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Puritans --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170416:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Falſe-Teacher TRIED and CAST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſubject vſeful at all times, and but too ſeaſonable for the preſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Brinſley <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel at Great</hi> Yarmouth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. T.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Newberry,</hi> in Cornhil neer to the Royal Exchange. 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170416:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170416:2"/>
            <head>To all the truly well-affected and well-meaning Souls in the Town of Great <hi>Yar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth,</hi> who are not willing to be deceived in matters of greateſt concernment.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>(Dearly beloved in the Lord)</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>PAſsing along through this <hi>Chapter</hi> (as I have done the former) in a weeke dayes <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> I fell with this <hi>Text;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:170416:3"/>meeting with a <hi>ſubject</hi> but two ſeaſonable for the preſent times, (and I wiſh I might not ſay for this place), I have not unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly given way to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then uſual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements. And what the Lord hath ſo given in to me, I now preſent unto you. Wherein you have onely another <hi>ſtroke</hi> given to the ſame <hi>nail</hi> that was ſometimes ſince faſtened by a
<note n="*" place="margin">The falſe Apoſtle tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by Mr. <hi>William Bridge.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>maſter</hi> of the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> The Lord grant that it may ſo enter, and ſtick in your
<pb facs="tcp:170416:3"/>hearts, as that there may not be any door there left o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, to let in them whom you are forbiden to receive into your
<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>John.</hi> 10.</note> 
               <hi>Houſes.</hi> Of this ſort ſome, and too many have <hi>crept in</hi> already among you. And if like <hi>liberty</hi> be ſtill indulged, I may (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>Prophetical ſpirit</hi>) tell you, you muſt expect yet more, and thoſe more dangerous. What your <hi>duty</hi> in reference to them is, you have here held forth. The Lord make you truly and conſcientiouſly wiſe in the diſcharge of it. To whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:170416:4"/>grace commending you, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>One deſirous to watch for your ſouls.<hi>John Brinſley.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Yarmouth</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 10.1657.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170416:4"/>
            <head>THE <hi>FALSE-TEACHER Tryed and Caſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 2.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And thou hast tryed them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them lyars.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this,
<note place="margin">Diviſion of the Context.</note> and the following <hi>verſe,</hi> we have the <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> which the <hi>Son of man,</hi> the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> giveth of and to the <hi>Angel</hi> (the <hi>Miniſter</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi>) of the Church of <hi>Epheſus:</hi> which commendation we have here firſt <hi>propounded,</hi> then <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded. Propounded</hi> in the former part of this verſe: 1. In a <hi>general</hi> way, <hi>[I know thy works,]</hi> then in <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170416:5"/>inſtancing in ſome of thoſe works which he took ſuch ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of; which were three, his <hi>Labor,</hi> his <hi>Patience,</hi> his <hi>Zeal;</hi> ſhewed in <hi>not bearing with thoſe that were evil.</hi> Then <hi>expounded</hi> in the ſequel:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Explanat ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, quaſi retro v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtigia legens,</hi> Pare. in Text.</note> where he again toucheth upon each of theſe three particulars; Onely in a <hi>reiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade way,</hi> inverting the order, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtom of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> (which we often meet with in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) beginning firſt with the laſt; 1. Shewing how and wherein this <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> had expreſſed his <hi>zeal</hi> in not bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thoſe which were evil, <hi>viz.</hi> in his proceeding againſt <hi>falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> falſe teachers, whom upon the Tryal he had found to be lyars. <hi>[And thou haſt tryed them, &amp;c.]</hi> Secondly, What his <hi>patience</hi> was, and wherein he had ſhewed it, <hi>viz.</hi> In bearing much from thoſe whom he could not bear with, [<hi>And haſt born, and haſt patience, verſe</hi> 3.] Thirdly, What his <hi>labour</hi> was, even an unwearied in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour of doing ſervice to God and his Church, <hi>[And for my name ſake haſt laboured, and haſt not fainted,]</hi> It is the firſt of theſe I have now to deal with.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170416:5"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>And haſt tryed.]</hi> Wherein we have two things declared,</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">Parts of the Text. whom and what.</note> 
               <hi>What evil ones</hi> thoſe were which this <hi>Angel</hi> was ſo zealous againſt, could not bear, And</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>What he did to them.</hi> What e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ones; the <hi>falſe Apoſtles [Them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not]</hi> What he did to them. He tryed and convicted them. <hi>[Thou haſt tryed them and found them lyars.]</hi> Upon theſe look we ſeverally by way of <hi>Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">The perſons dealt with.</note> The <hi>Perſons</hi> whom this <hi>Angel</hi> could not bear. <hi>[Them which ſay they are Apoſtles, but are not.]</hi> Such there were ſome, and thoſe not a few, in thoſe <hi>proto-primitive</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> times. Strange that there ſhould be ſo, yet ſo there were. As in the times of the <hi>Prophets</hi> there were <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo in the times of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> there were <hi>falſe Apoſtes,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is the Apoſtles word. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. <hi>For ſuch are falſe Apoſtles.</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſ.</hi> And what were theſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What true <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were,
<note place="margin">Falſe Apoſtle what.</note> we know; ſuch as were immediately ſent
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170416:6"/>by Chriſt to preach the Goſpel to the whole world. Of this ſort were the twelve, who received their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from their Lord &amp; Maſter <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whil'ſt he was with them upon earth; to whom afterwards was added <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> who was ſubſtituted in the room of <hi>Judas.</hi> And ſuch was <hi>Paul,</hi> who received the like immediate Commiſſion from Chriſt himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in heaven. Theſe were <hi>true Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> who being thus called, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their calling by preaching of the <hi>true Goſpel.</hi> And from hence we may learn what thoſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> were: Which were of two ſorts (as the <hi>falſe prophets</hi> alſo were, and as Tyrants are ſaid to be,
<note place="margin">Falſe apoſtles of two ſorts.</note> 
               <hi>Titulo &amp; Exercitio,</hi>) Some in reſpect of their <hi>calling</hi> onely, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in reſpect of their <hi>Doctrine</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</p>
            <p>Firſt,
<note place="margin">1. In reſpect of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</note> Some in reſpect of their <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> ſuch as <hi>ſaid they were Apoſtles, but were not.</hi> Such as pretended to an immediate Commiſſion from Chriſt, that they were immediately called and ſent by him as the true <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> were, when as they were not ſo in truth. Such were thoſe whom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170416:6"/>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpeaketh of in that Text laſt cited,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſeudoapoſtolos iſtos voc at non, ut ego quidem opinor, quod ſalſam aliquam doctrinam ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſent, &amp;c.</hi> Bez. Gr. Annot. in Loc.</note> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13. <hi>Falſe Apoſtles:</hi> ſo called (as <hi>Beza</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conceive of it) not in regard of any <hi>falſe Doctrine</hi> which as yet they had preached, but in regard of their <hi>falſe-Title,</hi> the falſe claim which they made to that Office. They preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves to be <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> And the more to win upon the belief of the people, they carried themſelves like <hi>Apoſtles, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt</hi> (as it there followeth;) imitating them both in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>life,</hi> which they did as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as they are there deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed) <hi>deceitful workers,</hi> out of a by and ſiniſter reſpect, not ſeeking <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but <hi>themſelves;</hi> not his glory, or the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his people, but their own temporal advantage. Even as <hi>Satan the prince of darkneſs,</hi> is ſometimes <hi>transformed into an angel of light,</hi> (as the Apoſtle there goeth on verſ. 14.) ſuggeſting things vvhich ſeem to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of piety and zeal and holineſſe, as if the motion proceeded from a holy and bleſſed <hi>angel,</hi> whereas he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth nothing leſs, but under that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170416:7"/>pretence to deceive poor ſimple ſouls. So did thoſe <hi>falſe apoſtles.</hi> They pretended themſelves to be the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of Chriſt, and they held forth his Doctrine, ſo imitating and perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating the true <hi>apoſtles</hi> (as the <hi>Devil</hi> did <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.) but as they were <hi>falſe</hi> in the former, ſo in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Not being what they would bee thought, they did not intend what they pretended to. And upon this account were they called <hi>falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Others there were who,
<note place="margin">2 In reſpect of their Doctrine</note> as falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pretending to the like calling, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Apoſtles</hi> they were broachers of <hi>Lyes,</hi> Errours, Hereſies, dangerous and pernitious Doctrines. Such <hi>falſe teachers</hi> there were many in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times Such were thoſe whom they in their <hi>Synodall Letter</hi> written from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> gave warning to the Churches of, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.24. <hi>We have heard that certain which went out from us have troubled you with words, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting your ſouls, &amp;c.</hi> Some who pretended themſelves to be Apoſtles, or at leaſt to have been ſent forth by the Apoſtles, with a Commiſſion to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170416:7"/>preach, they brought doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to theirs, doctrines deſtroying the very foundation of the Goſpel, and ſo tending to ſubvert the faith of believers, crying up the Law; (the <hi>ceremonial</hi> law) as being ſtill in force. And ſuch <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> there were ſome in this Church of <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Such falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers in <hi>Pauls</hi> time in the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus.</hi>
               </note> So much wee may collect from that which <hi>Paul</hi> writeth to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle</hi> 1.3. where he deſireth him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to the end that he might charge ſome <hi>that they preach no other Doctrine.</hi> No doctrine contrary to, or diverſe from that which <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, and other of the Apoſtles had preached, which it ſeemeth there were ſome that then did.</p>
            <p>And as there were ſome ſuch <hi>falſe teachers</hi> then in that Church,
<note place="margin">More foretold to follow</note> ſo the ſame Apoſtle foretelleth it that there ſhould come more, and thoſe more dangerous after his departure. So he telleth the <hi>Elders</hi> of that Church, whom he wiſheth to be ſo much the more cautelous and circumſpect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. &amp;c. <hi>Take heed to your ſelves, and to all the flock over which the Holy Ghoſt hath
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170416:8"/>made you Overſeers, &amp;c. For I know, this, that after my departure ſhall grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous wolves enter in among you, not ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the flock;</hi> (as bloody <hi>perſecutors,</hi> ſo <hi>Heretical Teachers,</hi> who by their falſe doctrines ſhould make a prey of the ſouls of men;) <hi>alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe ſpeaking perverſe things to draw away diſciples after them,</hi> ſuch as ſhould be broachers of falſe and heretical doctrines, out of an ambition to make themſelves ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and popular.</p>
            <p>And what he foretold,
<note place="margin">Which accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly came to paſſe.</note> afterwards came accordingly to paſſe. In the dayes of this our Apoſtle and Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Saint <hi>John</hi> (who ſurvived the reſt of the Apoſtles) there were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſuch <hi>falſe teachers</hi> who troubled theſe Churches of <hi>Aſia</hi> with their he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical doctrines. So much we may take notice of from what he ſaith, 1 <hi>Epiſtle</hi> 4.1. <hi>Many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> And again, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. verſe 7. <hi>Many deceivers have entred into the world.</hi> Such were thoſe famous (infamous) Hereticks, <hi>Ebion</hi> and <hi>Corinthus,</hi> and ſome others, who whileſt they cried up themſelves the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170416:8"/>
               <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of Chriſt, they were ſworn enemies to him, crying down his <hi>Divinitie,</hi> his Godhead (as the <hi>Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (their off-ſpring) at this day do.) Againſt whom Saint <hi>John</hi> purpoſely ſet himſelf as in the beginning of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> ſo in the firſt and ſecond <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> And moſt probably ſome ſuch were theſe whom our Text ſpeaketh of. <hi>They ſaid they were Apoſtles,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending themſelves to be ſent by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But ſuch they were not, no true Apoſtles, whether for their <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> or <hi>Doctrine.</hi> In both upon due tryal they were found <hi>Lyars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And were there ſuch in thoſe times whilſt the true <hi>Apostles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were yet living,
<note place="margin">No wonder that there are ſuch in after ages. <hi>Quòd ſi haec cùm fuit Ecc eſiae Chriſtianae conditio, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitibus adhuc ipſis veris Apoſtolis, quis miretur noſtri temporis ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem Apoſto i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam jactantes, qui nè Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni quidem ſint?</hi> Bez. Gr. Anno. in Text.</note> what wonder then that there ſhould be ſuch in after ages? what wonder that there ſhould be one pretending to <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal authoritie,</hi> to be <hi>Peters ſucceſſor,</hi> which the Pope doth? what wonder that there ſhould be ſome others who pretend to an <hi>immediate call</hi> from God, to be ſent by him, and to have received <hi>Revelations</hi> from him, who thereupon take upon them to broach <hi>new Doctrines,</hi> diverſe from,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170416:9"/>nay contrarie to that which is held forth in the word? which let it not trouble thoſe who behold it. If there were ſuch in the <hi>Apostles</hi> times, who were able to <hi>look through</hi> ſuch pretenders, to ſee their inſide (as <hi>Peter</hi> did by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> when he told him, <hi>I perceive that thou art in the gall of bitterneſs and bond of iniquitie, Acts</hi> 8.23.) who were able of their own knowledge to convince them, how much more now? But I paſs on.</p>
            <p>Having ſeen who,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">What this Angel did to them; where His un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, the iſſue of it.</note> and what theſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> were, come we now in the next place to ſee <hi>what this Angel did to them.</hi> He <hi>Tryed</hi> them, and <hi>found them Lyars:</hi> wherein we have two things. His <hi>undertaking</hi> and the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of it. His undertaking <hi>[Thou hast tried them.]</hi> The Iſſue of that Tryal <hi>[And hast found them Lyars.]</hi> of theſe ſeverally, beginning with the firſt, the <hi>undertaking</hi> of this <hi>Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou haſt tryed them.</hi>]
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (ſaith the Original) which word coming firſtly from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>transfodio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">His underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, he Tryed them.</note> 
               <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adigo,</hi> to pierce through, it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifieth an <hi>exact ſcrutin</hi> and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170416:9"/>of a thing. Like as when a thing is pierced through, it is tryed what is within, whether it be ſound or no. And ſuch a tryal it was that this <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> made of theſe <hi>Teachers.</hi> Not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their word, not truſting their outſide, he made a thorow tryal of them. <hi>Exploraris</hi> (ſaith <hi>Beza;</hi>) thou haſt proved them, by making a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch concerning them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> And <hi>thus are all ſuch Teachers to be tryed;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Teachers to be Tryed.</note> mark it this is the Doctrine I am now to proſecute. Such as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to a <hi>Call</hi> from God, ſhall bring any <hi>new Doctrines,</hi> contrary to, or diverſe from that which the word holdeth forth, and the Church hath received, they are to undergo an exact ſcrutinie, to be throughly try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For this we ſhall need no other warrant then that known Text of Saint <hi>John,</hi> which is expreſs and full, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. <hi>Believe not every ſpirit, but try the ſpirits, whether they be of God, or no.</hi>] <hi>Every ſpirit,</hi> that is, every <hi>Doctor,</hi> or <hi>Doctrine.</hi> Every <hi>Teacher</hi> that ſhall pretend to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; or every <hi>Doctrine</hi> which ſhall be held forth under the name of a <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170416:10"/>as received by <hi>inſpiration</hi> from Gods Spirit. Theſe are not preſently to be received, believed, but to be tryed, proved. This is that which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> requires concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe who pretending to a gift of <hi>Propheſie</hi> ſhould ſtand up to ſpeak in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.29. <hi>Let the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſpeak two or three, and let the other judge.</hi> Such as pretended to a gift of Propheſie (which in thoſe times was not rare) they were to be heard by the Church, but not preſently believed, but they muſt be tried by thoſe who had the gift of diſcerning ſpirits, the other true Prophets, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they had ſuch a gift as they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to, and whether that which was ſpoken by them were by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſpirit of God, or whether it were a fancie of their own brain, a humane or Diabolical deluſion.</p>
            <p>Yea,
<note place="margin">Generally, all Teachers.</note> thus are all <hi>Teachers,</hi> and all <hi>Doctrines</hi> to be tryed. That Rule and direction of the Apoſtle is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Proving all things. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, All things,</hi> All Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, all Doctrines and opinions, by whomſoever held forth. This is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170416:10"/>one of the things for which thoſe <hi>Beraeans</hi> are commended, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>more noble</hi> then ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. for that, when they heard the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Doctor of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, the chief teacher of his time, Preach, they brought his Doctrine to the Teſt, trying and examining <hi>whether thoſe things which were ſpoken and delivered by him were ſo,</hi> whether they were conſonant and agreeable to the Doctrine of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> that Doctrine which they had already received. Now if <hi>true Apostles</hi> were thus to be tryed, how much more <hi>falſe</hi> ones, thoſe who have nothing to prove them ſo, but their <hi>word.</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> had. He had the <hi>ſignes of an Apostle</hi> (as he tels his <hi>Corinthians,</hi>) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thoſe <hi>wonders and mighty deeds</hi> which he there ſpeaketh of, his miraculous works, ſome of which are recorded in that Chapter foregoing <hi>Acts</hi> 16. for which (no queſtion) he was then famous through the Churches, and yet they try his Doctrine, and for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170416:11"/>are commended.
<note place="margin">Eſpecially ſuſpitious ones.</note> How much more then are they to be tryed, who have nothing but their <hi>word,</hi> to gain credit to their <hi>calling</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine?</hi> As for their <hi>works,</hi> it may be they are ſuch as juſtly render them ſuſpicious. And being ſuch, great Reaſon that the Churches of Chriſt ſhould be jealous of them, and ſo, try them before they truſt them.</p>
            <p>Great <hi>Reaſon</hi> for it (I ſay,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the <hi>Danger</hi> firſt <hi>of,</hi> then <hi>In</hi> being deceived.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">The danger of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by falſe Teachers, which are</note> 
               <hi>The danger of being deceived,</hi> which credulous and ſimple ſouls are very ſubject to by ſuch Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>Falſe Teachers</hi> which</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Many for their Number.</note> Are <hi>many.</hi> This is the Reaſon which Saint <hi>John</hi> giveth why he would have thoſe to whom he writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to make this Tryal, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. (a Text forecited,) <hi>Try the ſpirits,</hi> &amp;c. why? <hi>Becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> Where there are many deceivers, many cheaters, many <hi>Trepanners</hi> (as now they call ſome of that crue) walking abroad, men had need to try before they truſt. And ſuch is the condition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170416:11"/>of the world in reſpect of <hi>falſe Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, (ſpiritual Trepanners.)</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſome ages are fuller of them then other, yet in all ages there are many.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Subtile for their nature.</note> And (ſecondly) as they are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for their number, ſo they are very <hi>crafty and ſubtile for their nature:</hi> It was <hi>Satans</hi> practiſe at the firſt, when he went about to deceive the woman, he made uſe of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> ſpeaking in and by that creature which (as the Text ſaith,) <hi>was more ſubtile then any beaſt of the field, Gen.</hi> 3.1. Such was and is that Creature, being natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmooth and gliding, winding and inſinuating, and craftie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And hereupon <hi>Satan,</hi> who himſelf is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>old Serpent, Revel.</hi> 12.9. he maketh choice of that creature to convey his firſt Temptation and poiſonous ſuggeſtion by. And in a like way doth he deceive her <hi>poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie,</hi> ſtill making uſe of <hi>Serpents,</hi> ſubtile heads, <hi>ſharp</hi> wits, ſmooth tongues, inſinuating ſpirits, for the conveying of the poiſon of hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and damnable doctrines by them. So as ſimple ſouls, being over-cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170416:12"/>(as that their <hi>mother</hi> was) they are apt to be deceived by them, by their <hi>ſubtiltie,</hi> (of which the Apoſtle (making uſe alſo of this alluſion) ſpeaketh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.3.)</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> As alſo by their <hi>Innocencie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deceiving by their Lives, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times are ſeemingly pious.</note> Such was the <hi>Serpent</hi> at the firſt, (as all the other creatures were) innocent and harmleſs. And ſuch <hi>falſe teachers</hi> oftimes ſeem to be; very innocent in their lives, exemplarie for their ſtrictneſs. Such were the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> in our Saviours time, <hi>whited Sepulchres,</hi> (as he cals them <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.27.) And ſuch were thoſe <hi>falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> whom he deſcribeth <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15. they were ſuch as came in <hi>ſheepes cloathing,</hi> ſeemingly moſt innocent creatures. And ſuch were thoſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> giveth warning to his <hi>Coloſſians</hi> of, very ſtrict (no queſtion) themſelves in thoſe obſervances which they taught and preſſed upon others, of which the Apoſtle ſaith that they had in them <hi>a ſhew of humilitie, and neglecting of the bodie, not in any honour to the ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fleſh, Col.</hi> 2.23. They were very temperate, very abſtemious.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170416:12"/>And ſuch were divers of the ſame ſtamp in after ages. Among whom one Sect was known and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the name of <hi>Encratitae;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>vide Danaeum</hi> in Auguſt. <hi>de Haereſibus cap.</hi> 15.</note> ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from their extraordinarie conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and abſtinence, which was ſuch as that they abſteined not onely from unlawful luſts, but alſo from <hi>Marriage,</hi> and from eating any kinde of <hi>fleſh,</hi> as alſo <hi>wine,</hi> not ſo much as allowing it in the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the great abuſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) but uſing <hi>water</hi> inſtead of it; yet holding forth foul and heretical Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. And ſuch <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten are, (as many <hi>Monkes</hi> and <hi>Fryars</hi> at this day,) eminent for ſtrictneſs in their lives, and converſations.</p>
            <p>And as their <hi>Lives,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 By their doctrins, ſome of which are ſound, and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and their errours plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> ſo their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> many of them (it may be) are true and <hi>Orthodox,</hi> yea <hi>pious</hi> and very uſeful, which they Preach and preſs, making uſe of them as <hi>Coy-Ducks,</hi> to bring in their Errors after them. And for their <hi>Errors,</hi> happily they are very plauſible and taking, ſpecious at the firſt hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; having (as the Apoſtle there ſaith, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a ſhew of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170416:13"/>yea of <hi>Pietie,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs.</hi> Thus did theſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> ſpoken of by Saint <hi>Paul, transform themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt; the miniſters of Satan transform themſelves into the Miniſters of righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 11.13, 15. And thus do <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times transform themſelves into true; acting their parts, putting on the habits, and ſpeaking with the tongues of the true ſervants, the faithful Miniſters of Chriſt. Being (as I ſaid) <hi>Innocent,</hi> (if not <hi>Exemplarie</hi>) in their lives, holding forth plauſible Errors, and thoſe mixed with many ſweet and precious truths; which are like wine, or ſome other pleaſant liquor, wherewith <hi>poiſon</hi> being mixed, it is taken and ſwallowed down without ſuſpicion: upon this Account then Teachers are to be tryed. There being ſo many <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> and many of them ſo <hi>ſubtile,</hi> great is the danger <hi>of being deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> And (ſecondly,) as great danger <hi>in being deceived.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The danger in being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them.</note> As it is in drinking of <hi>poiſon,</hi> there is great danger to the Body, ſo there is in receiving and drinking in heretical doctrines, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170416:13"/>are no other but poiſon to the ſoul: what the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hereſie the Poyſon of Aſpes.</note> (and from him the Apoſtle) ſaith of <hi>wicked men</hi> in general, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.13. It may well be applied to <hi>Heretical</hi> Teachers in particular, <hi>The poiſon of aſpes is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their lips.</hi> The poiſon of the Aſpe (or viper) is ſecretly inſtilled, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any great ſenſe or pain, yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately mortal to the perſon that is bitten, or ſtung by it, who being thereby caſt into a dead ſleep, he never waketh more: And truely ſuch is the nature of falſe and <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal doctrine,</hi> it is ſecretly and inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly inſtilled into the ſoul; but oftentimes proves mortal to it, caſting the ſoul into a dead ſleep from which it never wakes, till it come in hell. So deſperate oftimes is the conditions of poor deluded ſouls. Like as the Apoſtle ſaith of the <hi>Seducers,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. ſo it proves often true in the <hi>ſeduced, They wax worſe and worſe,</hi> going on from one error to another, from a leſſer to a greater, from <hi>Schiſme</hi> to <hi>Hereſie.</hi> A truth ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experimented in many inſtances in this Nation of late times. How
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170416:14"/>many ſeemingly, and hopefully well meaning ſouls have there been, who by hearkening to ſuch Teachers, <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> have been ſo impoiſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their Doctrines, as that now they are ſwollen thereby, ſo ſwollen with ſpiritual pride (the worſt of prides) as that they refuſe and ſcorn the advice of whatſoever <hi>ſoul-Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi> the true Miniſters of Chriſt, ſo as unleſs God undertake them in a more then ordinary way, there is little hope of their recovery? Such, and ſo great is the danger <hi>in being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived</hi> by ſuch Teachers.</p>
            <p>So our firſt parent,
<note place="margin">The ſerpents deceiving our firſt parent how dangerous to her, and her poſterity.</note> our great Grandmother <hi>Eve</hi> found it by ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. <hi>Being deceived</hi> by <hi>Satan</hi> ſpeaking in the <hi>Serpent, ſhe was in the tranſgreſſion</hi> (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hath it) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14. Thereby ſhe became guiltie of that firſt tranſgreſſion, which, had not infinite mercy ſtept in, had brought everlaſting ruine upon her, and all her Poſteritie. And how fatal hath this proved to many others, their hearkning to Satan ſpeaking in and by unſuſpected inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? we know what happened to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170416:14"/>King <hi>Ahab,</hi> whileſt he hearkned to his <hi>falſe prophets,</hi> following the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel which they gave him, bidding him to <hi>go up to Ramoth Gilead and proſper,</hi> an arrow ſtrikes him between the joynts of his harneſs, giving him a mortal wound (as you have the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.32.) And what happened to his Body, how often hath it happened unto the ſouls of many? who by hearkening unto <hi>falſe teachers</hi> have met with, ſome <hi>Errors,</hi> ſome <hi>Hereſie,</hi> ſome dangerous and damnable Doctrine; which hath been as an <hi>Arrow,</hi> piercing their hearts, giving them a deadly wound, and upon this account again great Reaſon that <hi>Teachers ſhould be tryed,</hi> before they be truſted.</p>
            <p>To theſe ſome other might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trying make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of men.</note> To <hi>receive and believe teachers</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>word;</hi> to receive their <hi>Perſons</hi> and believe their <hi>Doctrine</hi> without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination and tryal, is to <hi>make men the ſervants of men;</hi> which Chriſtians ought not to be, <hi>ye are bought with a price</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle,) <hi>be not ye the ſervants of men,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. Chriſtians being bought with a price, <hi>redeemed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170416:15"/>with the precious blood of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> explaines it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19.) and ſo made his ſervants, his freemen, they are not to mancipate and inſlave themſelves to any other what ever; ſpecially to inſlave their <hi>ſouls</hi> and <hi>conſciences,</hi> ſo as to ſuffer any man whatever to have the command over them. This is that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſo ſmartly reproves his <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> for, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. <hi>Ye ſuffer if a man bring you into bondage.</hi> This did the <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> their <hi>new teachers,</hi> tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing over their conſciences, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing upon them their Ceremonial obſervances. And this they ſuffered, ſubmitted to, though contrary to their <hi>Goſpel libertie.</hi> Such was their eſteem of thoſe <hi>new Teachers,</hi> that they readily received their <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and conformed to their <hi>injunctions,</hi> though diverſe from, and contrarie to that which they had received. But this Chriſtians ought not to do; Being Chriſts freemen, they are not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave themſelves to any, ſo as to yield an abſolute credence to their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, and dictates. This is an honour which is peculiar onely unto
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170416:15"/>
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who being an <hi>abſolute Lord</hi> over his people, juſtly challengeth their abſolute dependance upon him, and obedience to him; ſo as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his word without Tryal. Not ſo any other; who, (be what they will, yet are ſubject to miſcarry. <hi>Let God be true, and every man a Lyar</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) Rom. 3.4. <hi>A Lyar,</hi> and that both <hi>paſſively</hi> and <hi>actively;</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be deceived himſelf, and ſo to deceive others. Such are the beſt of men being left to themſelves, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then as they are aſſiſted and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the ſpirit of truth. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Jefus Chriſt</hi> he is <hi>the truth</hi> (as he ſaith of himſelf <hi>John</hi> 14.6.) And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be believed on his word. Not ſo any other whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Angel. Not that we have dominion over your Faith</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. They are not to be received but upon tryal. They who <hi>ſaid they were apoſtles,</hi> were yet tryed by this <hi>angel of the Church,</hi> who is here commended by his Lord and maſter for ſo doing. [<hi>I know thy works,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou haſt tryed them which ſay they are apoſtles,</hi> &amp;c.] Thus have you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170416:16"/>the <hi>doctrinal confirmation &amp; Illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> That which remains is <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Applic. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Too great cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulty taxed.</note> Where (in the firſt place by way of <hi>reprehenſion</hi>) I might take a juſt occaſion to tax and cenſure the too <hi>great credulitie</hi> that is to be found among many Chriſtians in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at this day; who if any come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, pretending to <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> they preſently receive him, hearken to him, believe him, giving intertainment to his <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>doctrine,</hi> not trying, not examining the one, or the other; By which means they become guiltie of that, which the Apoſtle cautions his <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> againſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.14. Children-like, they are <hi>toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of doctrine:</hi> yea ſome of them carried (like as thoſe <hi>ſwine</hi> were, into which the devils entred, of which the ſtorie tels us that they <hi>ran violently down a ſteep place into the ſea, Mat.</hi> 8.32.) into moſt pernicious, dangerous and damnable errors. And how ſhould it be otherwiſe? They who will truſt without trial muſt make account at one time or other to be deceived.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170416:16"/>Which that none of you may be.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe, </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtians ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to try Teachers.</note> By way of <hi>exhortation</hi> (in the ſecond place) let me deſire you to <hi>propound this Angel as a pattern for your imitation.</hi> See that you try before you truſt. This will you do in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>civil</hi> concernment. How much more then in <hi>ſpirituals,</hi> in things which concern the welfare of your ſouls, your eternal ſalvation? Herein you cannot be too wary. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed what <hi>Teachers</hi> you hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to: Yea, though haply they be of <hi>great name</hi> and note, much cryed up by many, what ever their <hi>parts</hi> and <hi>gifts</hi> be; yea, what ever their <hi>life</hi> and <hi>converſation</hi> be, yet do not ſo far make your ſelves ſervants to any of them, as to pinne your faith upon their ſleeve; be not <hi>over credulous,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if they be ſuch as theſe in the Text, ſuch as pretending to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary calling, ſhall hold forth new doctrines, ſuch as the Church of God hath not been acquainted with. Now bee jealous of them, fearing (what you have juſt cauſe to do) that they are not what they pretend to be. <hi>They ſay they are Apoſtles, but are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170416:17"/>not,</hi> Therefore bring them to the trial.</p>
            <p>A thing which <hi>Chriſt himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">A thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</note> So he doth in this <hi>angel</hi> here, among whoſe good works hee reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons up this for one, his trial of ſuch; <hi>Thou haſt tried them which ſay they are apoſtles and are not.]</hi> This tended to his praiſe. Now this is one of the things which the Apoſtle willeth Chriſtians to have an eye unto, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>If there be any vertue, any praiſe,</hi> (any thing truly praiſeworthy from men, much more if commended by God) <hi>think on theſe things,</hi> ſo think of them as to do them. Now were there no other Argument, this alone ſhould be ſufficient to induce Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to this practice, doing this in a conſcientious way, with a reſpect to the honour of Jeſus Chriſt (which queſtionleſſe this Angel here did) for the aſſerting and vindicating of his name and truth, whatever they meet with from men, they ſhall have his approbation and commendation.</p>
            <p>But (ſecondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argument. </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">Commanded.</note>) this is not onely commended but alſo <hi>commanded.</hi> Thoſe forenamed Texts are expreſſe,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170416:17"/>being not onely <hi>counſels</hi> but <hi>precepts. Try the ſpirits, whether they be of God; Prove all things.</hi> So as this is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Liberty,</hi> but a <hi>duty,</hi> a thing not onely expedient but requiſite, not onely what may be done, but muſt be done. <hi>Teachers,</hi> eſpecially if ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, they muſt be <hi>tryed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But <hi>who ſhall try them?</hi> and <hi>How ſhall they try them?</hi> Two uſeful queſtions; Take the reſolution of each.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Who ſhall be the tryers of theſe teachers?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Who are to try them.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1 To this I anſwer, Firſt, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally</hi> all <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Generally all Chriſtians.</note> To them are thoſe forenamed <hi>exhortations</hi> direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of <hi>trying of ſpirits, and proving all things.</hi> General Leſſons for all <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> who, being <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> are made judges of all things. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.15. <hi>He that is ſpiritual judgeth all things,]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the ſpiritual man;</hi> not the <hi>Pope,</hi> to whom ſome of his Paraſites apply that Text. Nor yet onely the <hi>Clergy,</hi> (as they have been called) the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel, to whom cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in former ages hath appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Title, calling them <hi>ſpiritual</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170416:18"/>perſons in way of diſtinction from the (ſo called) <hi>Laity.</hi> But every <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> who is enlightened and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated by the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of God. He is this <hi>ſpiritual man,</hi> who <hi>judgeth all things,</hi> underſtanding and diſcerning the truth of God, ſo much as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his own ſalvation. And being thus qualified, he not onely may, but ought to exerciſe this his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon thoſe (whoever they are) that bring doctrines contrary to, or diverſe from that truth, <hi>trying them.</hi> This are private Chriſtians to do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe abilities, that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>ſpirit of diſcerning</hi> which God hath given them. But,</p>
            <p>Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>2</label> This are the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> after a more ſpecial manner to do.
<note place="margin">Specially the Angels of the Churches, the miniſters of Chriſt.</note> As it is in trying of gold, if any pieces be ſuſpicious, every one, before hee receiveth them, will try them for himſelf, having his <hi>ſcales</hi> for that purpoſe; but the Gold-ſmith doth this after a more exact manner, having not onely his <hi>ſcales</hi> for the <hi>weight,</hi> but his <hi>touch-ſtone</hi> for the met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. Thus though all Chriſtians are to try ſuſpicious <hi>teachers</hi> &amp; <hi>doctrines,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170416:18"/>yet the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt</hi> are to do it after a ſpecial manner,
<note place="margin">Miniſters Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by office.</note> they being <hi>tyrers by Office.</hi> Such were the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles</hi> in their times,
<note place="margin">Such were the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts.</note> who exerciſed this power upon divers, trying and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering them to bee what in truth they were, nothing leſſe then what they pretended. So did <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> upon <hi>Simon Magus, the father of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> (as he is called) a broacher and maintainer of divers blaſphemous and damnable Hereſies; <hi>Peter</hi> tryeth and diſcovereth him to be what in truth he was, not what he gave out himſelf to be, and was by many ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for, as you have the ſtory, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.21.23. And the like did <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> whom (as he ſaith) he <hi>delivered to Satan, that they might learn not to blaſpheme,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. laſt: proceeding againſt them by Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical cenſures for the Hereſie which they held forth, <hi>in denying the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> to whom <hi>Philetus</hi> alſo (as it ſeemeth) was join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whom upon the ſame account he taketh notice of, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.18, 19. And what himſelf did, he willeth his Evangeliſt <hi>Timothy</hi> alſo to doe the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170416:19"/>like. <hi>If a man teach otherwiſe</hi> (ſaith he to him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3.) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> preaching other doctrine then that which the Church had already recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Chriſt and his Apoſtles) <hi>and conſent not to wholeſom words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Christ, and to the doctrine which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godlineſs, from ſuch</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>withdraw thy ſelf;</hi> have no communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, whether <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Fraternal,</hi> but look upon them, (as they are) as contagious perſons, not fit for Chriſtian ſocietie. And the like he requires from <hi>Titus, A man that is an Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond admonition reject, Tit.</hi> 3.10. Thus did <hi>Paul</hi> ſet himſelf againſt the whole generation of <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> willing all the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt in a ſpecial manner to do the like.</p>
            <p>This did our Apoſtle and Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt Saint <hi>John,</hi> whoſe zeal againſt that infamous Heretick <hi>Cerinthus</hi> is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, with whom he would not ſo much as enter into the <hi>Bath,</hi> leaſt the houſes ſhould fall on his head;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Danaeum in</hi> Auguſt: <hi>de</hi> Hereſ. Chap. 8.</note> and at whom he is conceived to ſtrike (as elſewhere, in his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in his firſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170416:19"/>chapter ſo) in thoſe two places of his firſt Epiſtle, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 2.22. and 4.3. And the like did this <hi>angel</hi> here in the Text, the <hi>miniſter</hi> or <hi>miniſters</hi> of this Church of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> To him (or them) it is that this commendation is here given, for dealing with theſe <hi>falſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles.</hi> Not but that the Church al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo might concur herein, but he was the leader, having (as the firſt, ſo) the chief hand in it. And therefore is it that it is here attributed to him, <hi>to the angel of the Church of Epheſus write, I know thy works, thou haſt tryed them, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the like did the faithful <hi>mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of Chriſt in after ages,
<note place="margin">The Ancient fathers Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in this way.</note> many of which are famous for their zeal and activity in this way. As <hi>Juſtine Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Irenaeus, Tertullian, Cyprian, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine;</hi> all <hi>tryers of falſe Apoſtles,</hi> ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly &amp; zealouſly oppoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the falſe Teachers of their times. And the like work is incumbent upon all the Miniſters of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">A work in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all true mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; who</note> who being by their Office <hi>ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds,</hi> they are to take, and give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſuch <hi>wolves</hi> as come in <hi>ſheeps cloathing,</hi> plucking off their diſguiſes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170416:20"/>unmaſking, and diſcovering them to the <hi>ſheep,</hi> making them known to the people, that ſo they may not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by them.
<note place="margin">Should be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of falſe Teachers.</note> Being <hi>miniſters</hi> their place requires that they ſhould bee <hi>tryers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1 Able to do it.</note> Such as are in meaſure <hi>able</hi> to do this, to try Teachers, and their doctrines. Men endued with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and that in a more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary manner, ſo as they may be able not onely to <hi>exhort,</hi> but to <hi>convince.</hi> So the Apoſtle expreſſely requires it in a <hi>Biſhop,</hi> a Goſpel Miniſter, a <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi> (who in ſcripture language is ever meant by that name) <hi>a Biſhop</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>muſt be one that is able by ſound doctrine both to exhort, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the gain-ſayers, Tit.</hi> 1.9. both to hold forth true doctrine himſelf, and to diſcover errours in others, to try them. Such ones the Miniſters of Chriſt ſhould be; which where in meaſure they are not (as it is the lot of too many places in this Nation at this day) their flocks, the people committed to their charge, muſt needs bee expoſed to the greater haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170416:20"/> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And as they are to be <hi>pares operi,</hi> in meaſure able to do this,
<note place="margin">Active in it.</note> ſo they are to <hi>do it,</hi> laying forth their abilities in making this trial as occaſion is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered; looking out, as the <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> doth diſcover the enemie; from what quarter, or under what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe ſoever he cometh, ſo giving due and ſeaſonable notice thereof to the people. This (moſt probably) did this <hi>angel</hi> here in the Text, and for ſo doing he is commended. And herein let him be a patern to all the <hi>apoſtles of the Churches,</hi> the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> whom he hath ſet as <hi>watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> over his Church for this end. <hi>Son of man I have made thee a watchman to the houſe of Iſrael</hi> (ſaith the Lord to the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel) Ezech.</hi> 3.17. Now the <hi>watchman,</hi> as he is to <hi>take notice</hi> of thoſe which come into the Citie, ſo, (if <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> perſons,) he is to examine them. And ſo are the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt to take notice in a ſpecial manner what <hi>teachers</hi> they are that thruſt themſelves in upon the people committed to their charge, and being <hi>ſuſpicious</hi> (which all they are, who as the Apoſtle ſaith
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170416:21"/>of the ſeducers of his time 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.) <hi>creep into houſes,</hi> making it their firſt deſign to work upon the weaker ſex, to <hi>lead captive ſilly women,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>mulierculas,</hi> ſimple women which are apt to be miſled, inſtilling their new doctrines firſt into them, as the <hi>old Serpent</hi> did his, firſt into the <hi>woman,</hi> hoping afterwards to have the like ſucceſs that he had, to draw their husbands after them: they are to <hi>try</hi> them, to trie their <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> that ſo they may be known to the people. Thus have you the former of theſe queries reſolved: <hi>who they are that are to make this tryal.</hi> All <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>general,</hi> the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt in <hi>ſpecial.</hi> The ſecond fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>How is this Tryal to be made?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A point of large diſcourſe,
<note place="margin">How falſe Teachers are to be Tryed.</note> opening a wide field to him that would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. But this task I find happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken off of my hands, this work being already largely and fully done in a Sermon Preached not long ſince,
<note place="margin">The falſe Apoſtle try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Wid. Bridge.</hi>
               </note> though not in this very place, yet not far from it, even under the ſame roof, and upon this very Text, by a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170416:21"/>Reverend Brother, who hath alſo given an account of it to the world. So as I might wholly ſpare that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. But it being a point of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, and which needeth incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating in regard of the times where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into we are fallen, (and I wiſh I might not ſay the place wherein we live,) I ſhall for this once (in a good ſenſe) <hi>actum agere,</hi> ſpend a little time in putting of you in remembrance of what happily you may be too apt to forget.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> For anſwer then (to tread in thoſe obvious ſteps wherein he went before me,
<note place="margin">By their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Doctrine, Life.</note> The Tryal of falſe Teachers is to be made principally in, and by three things, their <hi>Calling, Doctrine, Life.</hi> By theſe three the <hi>true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of Chriſt are known, when their <hi>Calling</hi> is <hi>warrantable,</hi> their <hi>Doctrine Orthodox,</hi> their <hi>lives approveable. Now rectum eſt index ſui &amp; obliqui;</hi> that which declares a <hi>true Miniſter</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers a <hi>falſe.</hi> And ſo do theſe three, where they are not to be found.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tryal </seg>1</label> 1. Try them by their <hi>Calling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Calling.</note> If that be falſe, they cannot be <hi>true.</hi> This
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170416:22"/>is the Character which is given of falſe Prophets <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.21. <hi>I have not ſent theſe prophets, yet they ran.</hi> True Prophets, and ſo true <hi>Miniſters,</hi> have a <hi>miſſion</hi> and <hi>commiſſion</hi> from God, being ſent, and authorized by him: which they who are not, cannot perform what too many pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do; Preach the word. <hi>How ſhall they preach except they be ſent? Rom.</hi> 10.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">How Tryed.</note> But how ſhall it be known whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be rightly called, or no? A queſtion of great concernment, ſpecially in theſe times, wherein the <hi>calling</hi> of the true Miniſters of Chriſt is ſo much ſcrupled and queſtioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Calling of Teachery, Ex. traordinary, Ordinarie.</note> For anſwer hereunto take we notice of a <hi>twofold calling: Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie</hi> and <hi>Ordinary.</hi> Extraordinarie and <hi>Immediate,</hi> ordinary and <hi>Mediate.</hi> In the former way the <hi>prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were ſo called. So <hi>Paul</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes and aſſerts his Apoſtolical calling, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul an Apoſtle, not of men, neither by men,</hi>] not by any hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane anthoritie or ſuffrage, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any man for either <hi>Author,</hi> or
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170416:22"/>
               <hi>Inſtrument</hi> in that his calling, but he received it immediatly from Chriſt, as the twelve Apoſtles did. In the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter way the <hi>ordinarie Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt are called. Being, though not of, yet by <hi>men;</hi> receiving their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from Chriſt, but conveyed to them through the hands of men (or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily) <hi>impoſed</hi> and layed upon them. So it was in the Apoſtles time, as that charge given by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie</hi> doth clearly evidence it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Lay hands ſuddainly on no man;</hi> that is, admit no man into the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie without due conſideration of his fitneſs for that work, that one Ceremonie <hi>(Impoſition of hands)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by a <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> put for the whole action of <hi>Ordination.</hi> And ſo it hath been continued generally through the Churches of Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this day.</p>
            <p>Now then would we try a <hi>falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher?</hi> make trial of the <hi>calling</hi> which he pretends unto, whether <hi>Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie</hi> or <hi>ordinarie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Extraordinary Calling atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Gifts,</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Extraordinarie.</hi> Such a calling many ſince the Apoſtles times have layed claim to, pretending an <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170416:23"/>call</hi> from God, the like to that which the Apoſtles had; of which kind: there are not a few creeping a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the world at this day. Now how ſhall they be tried? why, by their <hi>Gifts.</hi> An <hi>Extraordinarie calling</hi> is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with <hi>extraordinarie gifts.</hi> So was the <hi>Apoſtles calling,</hi> it was attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>gift of tongues,</hi> Illiterate men ſpeaking the moſt learned Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages: And with the <hi>gift of working miracles.</hi> Thus <hi>Paul</hi> aſſerts &amp; vindicates the truth of his Apoſtleſhip 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>Truely</hi> (ſaith he, ſpeaking to his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> among whom <hi>(happily)</hi> there were ſome that queſtioned his calling) <hi>the ſignes of an Apoſtle were wrought among you in all patience, in ſignes and wonders and mighty deeds]</hi> miraculous works, by which he might be certainly known to be no leſs an Apoſtle then any of the twelve. So then, ſhall any pretend to ſuch a <hi>call,</hi> an immediate and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling? make enquirie for their <hi>Gifts,</hi> their <hi>Works.</hi> This was the <hi>Jews</hi> enquirie concerning <hi>Chriſt</hi> when they ſaw him take upon him that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie which he did, to alter <hi>cuſtoms</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170416:23"/>of long continuance, to reform and rectifie what the <hi>Sanhedrim,</hi> the great Counſel, and the reſt of the Prieſts tolerated, <hi>What ſigne ſheweſt thou unto us (ſay they) ſeeing thou doeſt theſe things? John</hi> 2.18. Hence they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, ſurely he held himſelf to be a Prophet, and thereupon they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him to give ſome ſigne of it, to evidence that his extraordinary cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by ſome extraordinary works. Thus were the Prophets of God or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily wont to evidence the truth of their calling.
<note place="margin">The caſe of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ex traordinary.</note> 
               <hi>Ordinarily</hi> (I ſay) though not alwayes: For we read of <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> to whom our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our giveth Teſtimonie, that he was <hi>a Prophet, yea more then a prophet, Mat.</hi> 11.9. that is, an excellent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Prophet, being the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald of Chriſt</hi> (as the next verſe ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth him forth) yet he wrought no miracles: So ſaith that Text, <hi>John</hi> 10.41. <hi>John did no miracle.</hi> But thus ordinarily it was. That <hi>John</hi> being a <hi>Prophet,</hi> ſhould not work miracles, the <hi>Jewes</hi> looked upon it as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted thing. This the other <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> before him uſually had done;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170416:24"/>Yea, and <hi>John</hi> himſelf, however hee wrought no ſuch miraculous works, as <hi>caſting out of devils, raiſing the dead, reſtoring ſight to the blinde;</hi> Yet he did that which was equivalent; he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told many things, all which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly came to paſſe. So the <hi>Jewes</hi> there take notice of it in the words following, <hi>All things that John ſpake of this man</hi> (of Chriſt) <hi>were true;</hi> the event verified all his predictions. Now let thoſe who pretend to the like vocation, to an <hi>extraordinary cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> to be the Meſſengers of God, of Chriſt, ſent by him in an immediate way, let them ſhew ſome ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, <hi>extraordinary gifts.</hi> Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe without any breach of charitie, they may bee ſuſpected, nay conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be, what theſe pretended <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> here were found to be, no other but <hi>Lyars.</hi> This for the <hi>extraordinary calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2. Ordinary calling tryal.</note> For the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> ſuch as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it, let them be examined and tried by their <hi>qualification</hi> and <hi>ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 By due qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For their <hi>qualification,</hi> whether they be indued with <hi>Miniſterial abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170416:24"/>and gifts.</hi> Thus it is, thoſe whom God calleth to an Office, he furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them with ſutable abilities for the diſcharge of it. Thus calling <hi>Saul</hi> to be <hi>King,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>He gave him another heart,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9. endowing him with heroical gifts and parts fit for the Government of his Kingdom: And thus ſending <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> he promiſeth <hi>to be with his mouth, and to teach him what he ſhould ſay,</hi> to make him fluent and eloquent, who natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally was <hi>ſlow and ſtammering</hi> (as he there ſaith of himſelf) <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.10, 11. And <hi>Iſay,</hi> being called to be a <hi>Prophet,</hi> hath his <hi>lips touched with a living coal from the Altar,</hi> a figure of the gift of the Holy Ghoſt fitting him for that ſervice, <hi>Iſay</hi> 6.7. And thus the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> though before (as I ſaid) <hi>illiterate fiſhermen,</hi> yet being called to that Office, they were endued with gifts ſutable thereunto. And ſo is it with all <hi>ordinary Miniſters</hi> and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. If <hi>called</hi> of God, they are alſo <hi>gifted</hi> by him: Though not all alike. There being <hi>diverſities of gifts</hi> (as the Apoſtle tels us) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4. Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities both for <hi>kinde</hi> and <hi>meaſure;</hi> and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170416:25"/>that of <hi>Miniſterial Gifts. To one is given by the ſpirit the word of wiſdom, to another the word of knowledge by the ſame ſpirit</hi> (as the eighth verſe there hath it) ſo as one excelleth in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> another in <hi>Application;</hi> the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer more properly the <hi>Doctors,</hi> the latter the <hi>Paſtors</hi> work (as <hi>Diodate</hi> there expounds it) Yet ſo as every one hath a <hi>miniſterial gift</hi> fitting him for the work to which he is called. <hi>The manifeſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withall</hi> (ſaith the verſe there foregoing (<hi>verſe.</hi> 7.). To every one that is called to any publick ſervice in the Church there is ſome gift given, whereby the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt</hi> ſheweth it ſelf in him, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring him in ſome kind uſeful and ſerviceble for the good and benefit of the comunity: where there is no ſuch <hi>gift</hi> to be found, let not ſuch a one be looked upon as a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of Chriſt, ſent by him. Here is the firſt thing to be enquired for in a <hi>Teacher,</hi> a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterial Qualification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2 A warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> The 2d. is a <hi>warrantable ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> a ſeting a part to the work. Thus was <hi>Paul</hi> ſeparated, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170416:25"/>(as he ſaith of himſelf) <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt called to be an Apoſtle, ſeparated unto the goſpel of God.</hi> So he was <hi>Intentionally</hi> in Gods deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and appointment <hi>from his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb,</hi> (as he tells his <hi>Galatians,</hi> chap. 1.15.), yea from <hi>Eternity</hi> in Godseverlaſting <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him for the ſervice; but <hi>actually</hi> ſet a part thereunto by the command of the <hi>Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> at what time he was ſent to preach the goſpel unto the Gentiles, of which we read, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. <hi>As they miniſtered unto the Lord, and faſted, the Holy Ghoſt ſaid; ſeparate mee Barnabas and Saul unto the work whereunto I have called them.</hi> Which in what way it was done the next verſe declareth <hi>[And when they had faſted and prayed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ordinarily done by Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands</note> 
               <hi>and layd their hands on them, they ſent them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</hi> Such was the manner of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Ordination,</hi> which the Church of God in after ages hath obſerved: by <hi>faſting,</hi> and <hi>prayer,</hi> and <hi>Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands,</hi> to ſet a part the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt unto the ſervice of the Church, the work of the Goſpel, which office being thus conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170416:26"/>on them they were thenceforth to <hi>attend</hi> to it,
<note place="margin">Setting them apart to the work of the Miniſtery.</note> to make it their, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> their <hi>work; Having a miniſtery, they were to wait on their miniſtring. Rom.</hi> 12.7. thus it hath been, and thus it ſhould bee.</p>
            <p>Not but that <hi>extraordinary caſes admit of extraordinary courſes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In ſome caſes how diſpenſed with.</note> Where there want fitting (I mean <hi>Miniſterial</hi>) hands to be impoſed, that Ceremony may be omitted. And, neceſitie requiring it, ſome other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice may be joyned with this. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith that he upon ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count ſometime <hi>laboured with his own hands,</hi> exerciſed a <hi>Handicraft,</hi> as he tells his <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.12. But in an ordinary courſe thus it ſhould not bee. The Miniſters of Chriſt are to be <hi>ſet a part</hi> to the <hi>work</hi> of their Miniſterie in a ſolemn manner; And being thus ſet apart, they are (as I ſaid) to <hi>make it their worke:</hi> which who ſo are not, or doe not, they give too juſt occaſion for others to ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and queſtion the truth of their calling.
<note place="margin">Services pro. to Miniſters not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken by others.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Specially when any being not ſo called ſhall take upon them in an
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170416:26"/>ordinary to way to intermeddle with ſuch ſervices as are properly and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarly <hi>Miniſteral,</hi> to diſpence ſuch <hi>Ordinances</hi> as are committed onely to them, as <hi>viz.</hi> not onely to preach the <hi>Word,</hi> but to adminiſter the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> (which it ſeemeth ſome, &amp; too many in theſe deſolate times that I ſay not in this place) adventure upon) this too plainly ſheweth and declareth them to be what they are, ſuch as <hi>ſay they are Apoſtles, but are not,</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to a calling which they have not. And thus I have done with the firſt of theſe three heads, wherein the Probation and Tryal of falſe teachers conſiſteth; the firſt thing wherein, and whereby they may, and are to be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, their <hi>calling;</hi> paſs we to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tryal </seg>2</label> The ſecond thing is their <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> This is the way which Saint <hi>John</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth for the trial of thoſe falſe Teachers of his time, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>Trye the ſpirits ſaith he whether they be of God, for many falſe prophets are gone out into the world.</hi> But how ſhould they try them? why, by their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> So it followeth. <hi>Hereby know
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170416:27"/>ye the ſpirit of God, every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God; and every ſpirit that confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is not of God.</hi> If their <hi>Doctrine</hi> be <hi>falſe</hi> they cannot be <hi>true.</hi> Falſe as to <hi>fundamentals,</hi> the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſtian Religion, denying, perverting them. This is that which St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith of thoſe <hi>falſe teachers</hi> which he fortelleth ſhould come into the Church 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who privilie ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Hereſies of deſtruction,</hi> wicked opinions and Doctrines, deſtructive to the ſouls of men, Such <hi>Teachers,</hi> who broach or hold forth ſuch opinions are moſt properly called <hi>falſe-teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers;</hi> who are to be tried by their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quest.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Q.</hi> How tried?</note> But the Queſtion here runs on. <hi>How ſhall their doctrine be tryed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A.</hi> By the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the Churches touch-ſtone.</note> To this the Anſwer is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious (it is ſo among <hi>Proteſtants</hi>) <hi>On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the word,</hi> the written word, the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> This is the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lydius Papis,</hi> the <hi>Churches touch-ſtone,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhe is to try <hi>Doctrines,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170416:27"/>
               <hi>teachers,</hi> for this expreſſe is that known Text of the Prophet <hi>Iſai,</hi> Chap. 8. verſ. 20. <hi>to the law and to the teſtimony,</hi> that is, to Gods word, the Scriptures, which is his teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, teſtifying of him, declaring his mind and will. Hereunto muſt they repair who would not be deceived by falſe teachers, bringing their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> to this <hi>tonch-ſtone,</hi> trying them by this. <hi>If they ſpeak not according to this word</hi> (ſo it followeth) <hi>it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no light in them] If they;</hi> if any, be they who they will, never ſuch pretenders to <hi>Illumination,</hi> yet ſhall they ſpeak otherwiſe then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word, holding forth any doctrine that is not conſonant and agreeable thereunto, they are no other but <hi>Impostors;</hi> this is an evident ſigne that their pretended light is no other but <hi>darkneſs.</hi> This is that which Chriſtians are to give heed to above what enter pretended <hi>Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> or <hi>Revelation.</hi> When <hi>Dives</hi> in the parable begged it of <hi>father Abraham,</hi> that he would <hi>ſend Lazarus to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe,</hi> that he might teſtifie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his breethren, what the ſtate of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170416:28"/>the damned was, what the torments of Hell were, which were prepared for ſuch as they were, what ſaith he to him? you have it <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.29. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham ſaith unto him, they have Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and the Prophets, let them hear them</hi>] intimating that the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the <hi>word</hi> is to be preferred before all other <hi>teſtimonies.</hi> They may be <hi>falſe,</hi> but this is undoubtedly <hi>true. Thy word is truth, Joh.</hi> 17.17. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this let Chriſtians repair, bringing the Doctrines of their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to this <hi>teſt.</hi> This was the <hi>Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> which thoſe <hi>Noble Bereans</hi> made uſe of in trying of <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine. How ever, looking upon him as a man ſent of God, they <hi>received the word from</hi> his mouth <hi>with readineſs of minde,</hi> yet <hi>they ſearched the Scriptures dayly, whether thoſe things were ſo, Act.</hi> 17.11. whether conſonant and agreeable to the written word. Like courſe are Chriſtians to take, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they meet with <hi>new doctrines,</hi> new to them, they are now to lay them to this rule. Thus doe <hi>tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in trying of <hi>weights</hi> and <hi>meaſures,</hi> they bring them to the <hi>ſtandard.</hi> If
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170416:28"/>they finde them either more or leſſe then that, they look upon them as not warrantable. And ſo is it with <hi>doctrines,</hi> if not exactly conſonant and agreeable to the written word, which God hath left as a <hi>ſtandard</hi> for his Church to try them by, if either more or leſſe, if any <hi>addition</hi> to the word, or <hi>ſubſtraction</hi> from it, if contrary to it, or diverſe from it, they are to bee looked upon as <hi>falſe,</hi> and he that teacheth them as a <hi>falſe teacher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it may be ſaid,
<note place="margin">Scriptures ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure to pri vate, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> 
               <hi>How ſhall private Chriſtians thus try them?</hi> It may be they are unlearned, weak and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not ſo able to judge the <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures;</hi> about the ſenſe whereof it is not alwayes agreed among learned men, the greateſt <hi>Clerks</hi> ſometimes differing in the expoſition of them. And how then ſhall they bee able to judge of them, ſo as to try doctrines by them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. To this it is anſwered, 1.
<note place="margin">Fundamentals clearly held forth.</note> That as for <hi>fundamental truths,</hi> neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be known and believed, they are plainly held forth, written as with a <hi>ſun-beam;</hi> So plainly ſet forth as that a weak eye may ſee them.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170416:29"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Obj.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">How is it that all doe not ſee them.</note> But if ſo, how then is it that ſome who are quick ſighted doe not? How is it that ſome who are learned conceived diverſly of them? They cannot ſee what others ſuppoſe they doe. As <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> they cannot ſee thoſe doctrines which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conceive to bee clearly held<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in the word,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label>
               <note place="margin">Not through any obſcurity in the word, But</note> To this it may be anſwered, this is not through any obſcurity or darkneſs in the word. But</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 It may be there is a <hi>beam in the eye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">There may be a beam in the eye.</note> which will not let it ſee what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in it ſelf is clear. Such a beam there is in the <hi>Papiſts</hi> eye, who being prejudiced againſt ſuch &amp; ſuch truths of God, as their <hi>great Apoſtle</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> will not give his allowance to, to whom they have inſlaved their judgements, they cannot (or rather will not) ſee them, though never ſo clearly held forth in the Word. And ſo may it bee with ſome others, who having the <hi>beam of ſome ſinful luſt</hi> or other in their eye, which they are willing to part with, they cannot ſee that which others doe, becauſe they are loath, not willing to ſee it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170416:29"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2 Or (ſecondly) in looking upon the ſcriptures they <hi>make uſe of falſe lights;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Falſe lights made uſe of.</note> not judging of it by <hi>its own</hi> light (which they ought to do) but by <hi>their own</hi> light. Either by the light of <hi>fancy</hi> which is the <hi>Quakers</hi> light, which he calls the <hi>Light within him.</hi> Or by the light of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> which is the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians</hi> light, which whileſt he is wholly guided by, no wonder he cannot ſee what is above reaſon; my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious doctrines, to be apprehended by faith, not comprehended by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Now they who ſhall make uſe of no other light but this dim one, no wonder if they cannot ſee what otherwiſe is clearly and plainly held<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth in the word.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3 To which I might adde,
<note place="margin">God in his juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment blinding the eye.</note> God in his juſt judgement ſometimes hideth that from the eyes of ſome, which through an ordinary work of that ſpirit he revealeth unto others. <hi>To you it is given to know the myſteries of the kingdome, but to them it is not given,</hi> Mat. 13.11. <hi>He hath blinded their eyes, and hardened their heart, that they ſhould not ſee with their eyes, nor under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with their heart, John.</hi> 12.40.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170416:30"/>This for <hi>fundamentals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>2</label> For <hi>other truths of God</hi> which are not ſo clear,
<note place="margin">Private Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to crave the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſpecially their Miniſters.</note> here private Chriſtians are to <hi>crave the help of others,</hi> ſuch as have more <hi>diſcerning ſpirits</hi> then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. In ſpecial of the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> who are (as I ſaid) <hi>Tryers by office;</hi> ſpecially their <hi>own Miniſters.</hi> To them in dubious caſes they are to repair, <hi>receiving the law from the mouthes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that I would have them <hi>ſee with their eyes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The people not to ſee with with their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters eyes.</note> So <hi>Romaniſts</hi> (Some of them) would have it, who cry up their <hi>implicit faith,</hi> willing and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring private Chriſtians to beleeve what the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, allowing them no other judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the doctrines of their teachers.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ad hoc quidem reſpondent, ex mente D.</hi> Joha nis <hi>Omnes fideles probare ſpiritus num ex Deo ſint, dìun illis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt qui ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum havent diſcretionem. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtius Com in loc.</hi>
               </note> So <hi>Eſtius</hi> tels us that ſome of them expound that forecited text of Saint <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 4.1. where he giveth that general direction to all, to, <hi>Try the ſpirits;</hi> This (ſay they) are private perſons to doe, not by themſelves, but by <hi>others,</hi> by thoſe who have the ſpirit of diſcerning, whom in this caſe they are to beleeve. For as it is in the <hi>natural body,</hi> the <hi>eye</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170416:30"/>onely ſeeth, though not onely for it ſelf, but for the whole Body. So is it in the <hi>Church</hi> (ſay they.) Here thoſe that have the ſpirit of diſcerning, the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters,</hi> they are to judge of Doctrines, which they doe, not onely for themſelves, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who by ſubmitting to their judgements, may be ſaid to <hi>try the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, viz.</hi> in, and by them. This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine (as <hi>Eſtius</hi> dares not avouch it) wee renounce. Not onely allowing but requiring (what the Scripture doth) that every one ſhould ſee for himſelf, with his own eyes. <hi>The juſt ſhall live by his faith, Hab.</hi> 2.4. not by the faith of his <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or yet of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though they may not ſee with their eyes,
<note place="margin">Yet may make uſe of their light.</note> yet they may make uſe of their <hi>light;</hi> As the <hi>wiſe men</hi> did of the <hi>Star</hi> to bring them to the place where Chriſt was. Such uſe both may and ought private Chriſtians to make of their <hi>Miniſters,</hi> who are as <hi>ſtars in the right hand of Chriſt, Rev.</hi> 1. make uſe of their light, their guidance, their direction. That ſo by the help there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they may come to ſee that in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170416:31"/>word, which otherwiſe may be dark and obſcure to them. Thus then let Chriſtians ſet upon the <hi>Tryal of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> and ſo of their <hi>Teachers</hi> by them.
<note place="margin">Directions in this Tryal. 1 Seek humble and meek ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Onely here, that they may not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, let them (firſt) <hi>ſeek humble and meek ſpirits:</hi> not <hi>thinking of themſelves above that which they ought to think, but thinking ſoberly</hi> (as the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires them) <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.3. Nor yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>captious and quarrelling ſpirits,</hi> ſeeking advantages againſt their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. So did the Prophet <hi>Jeremies familiars</hi> to him, they <hi>watched for his haltings, Ier.</hi> 20.10. And ſo dealt the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Thariſees</hi> by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> as St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, <hi>Luke</hi> 11. laſt, <hi>They laid wait for him, ſeeking to catch ſomething out of his mouth, that they might accuſe him.</hi> This is a thing which doth not become Chriſtians, who ought to be like unto their <hi>pattern; Chriſt</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who bids them, <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, Mat.</hi> 11.29. And being ſuch, they may now expect that God will reveal himſelf, and his truth to them. <hi>I will dwell with him that is of an humble ſpirit</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170416:31"/>ſaith the Lord) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. being rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as to ſupport and comfort, ſo to teach and inſtruct them. <hi>The meek will he guide in judgement, and the meek will he teach his way, Pſal.</hi> 25.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>2</label> And being humble and meek,
<note place="margin">Beware of miſtakes.</note> let them alſo be <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>warie;</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie leſt they <hi>miſtake the Doctrines</hi> which they hear, miſtake either <hi>words or ſenſe.</hi> Both theſe wayes we finde our <hi>Saviour</hi> miſtaken. In his <hi>words</hi> by <hi>Peter,</hi> and other his <hi>diſciples, John</hi> 21.22. where when <hi>Peter</hi> had propounded that curious enquirie concerning <hi>John, And what ſhall this man do?</hi> what ſhould become of him? our Saviour anſwereth him, <hi>If I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee?</hi> Here they miſtake him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving him to have ſpoken <hi>poſitively,</hi> that <hi>John</hi> ſhould not die, which went for currant among the Brethren; <hi>Yet</hi> (as the Text hath it) <hi>Jeſus ſaid not not unto him, He ſhall not die, but if I will that he tarry till I come, what is that to thee?</hi> And ſo in his <hi>ſence and meaning</hi> by the <hi>Jewes,</hi> who hearing what he ſaid to them, <hi>Deſtroy this Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in three dares I will raiſe it up
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170416:32"/>again,</hi> they underſtood him in a <hi>lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> ſenſe, as ſpeaking of the <hi>material Temple,</hi> whereas he ſpake <hi>figuratively,</hi> meaning that <hi>myſtical Temple, the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Body,</hi> as we have it, <hi>John</hi> 2.19, 20, 21. Thus are the <hi>Miniſters of Christ,</hi> though ſpeaking never ſo warily, ſubject to be miſtaken by their unwary auditours, which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who will make a true tryal of them muſt be warie of.
<note place="margin">Specially of willing ones.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Much more of <hi>willing and wilful miſtakes,</hi> of perverting their words, or meaning. A thing which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> chargeth upon ſome of his hearers, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.36. <hi>Ye have perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the words of the living God.</hi> This they had done by miſconſtruing, and making an ill uſe of what he, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Prophets ſaid unto them from the Lord. This let Chriſtians beware of. As alſo of <hi>ignorant and raſh cenſures,</hi> of <hi>ſpeaking evil of the things they underſtand not,</hi> which Saint <hi>Peter</hi> chargeth upon ſome in his time, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> from God.</note> 2.12. And being thus prepared, and <hi>diſtoſed,</hi> then in the laſt place,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>2</label> Let them <hi>ſeek a true underſtanding and ſound judgement from God;</hi> beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170416:32"/>that for themſelves which <hi>Paul</hi> doth for his <hi>Epheſians, Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>that God would give unto them the ſpirit of wiſdom and Revelation.</hi> A thing which he is ready to beſtow upon them who with honeſt and humble hearts ſeek it. <hi>Ask and it ſhall be given you</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>Luke</hi> 11.9. And what ſhall bee given them? why the <hi>holy Spirit.</hi> So the thirteenth verſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains it; <hi>If ye being evil know how to give good things to your children, how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give his ſpirit to them that ask him?</hi> Even that ſpirit of wiſdom. <hi>If any man lack wiſdom</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>James</hi> chap. 1. verſe 5.) ſpiritual wiſdom, <hi>Let him ask of God, which giveth to all men liberally,</hi> ſuch a portion as he ſeeth fitting and convenient for them. This for the ſecond Head; The Tryal of Teachers by their <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Tryal. </seg>3</label> The third and laſt is, their <hi>lives.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their lives.</note> As they are to be tryed by their <hi>Tongues,</hi> ſo by their <hi>hands,</hi> as by their <hi>words,</hi> ſo by their <hi>works.</hi> So it is with <hi>true Teachers,</hi> their works teſtifie of them. So ſaith our Saviour of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>John</hi> 10.25. <hi>The works that I do
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170416:33"/>in my Fathers Name they bear witneſſe of me,</hi> ſhewing him to be what he was, one ſent of God. And ſo they did of his <hi>Apoſtles. Truely the ſignes of an Apoſtle have been wrought among you in all patience</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to his <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12.) meaning his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and conſtancy in his ſufferings for Chriſt. Hee demeaned himſelf like an Apoſtle. So on the other hand <hi>falſe Teachers</hi> may bee tryed by their works, their practices. <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits</hi> (ſaith our Saviour ſpeaking of <hi>falſe prophets) Mat.</hi> 7.16. their <hi>works,</hi> their practiſes, which being exactly ſcanned, and narrowly pried into, will for the moſt part bee found unſuitable to their profeſſion. The <hi>Wolfe</hi> will be found under the <hi>ſheeps-skin;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Which in falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teachers often are not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveable.</note> under fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences a foul diſpoſition, ſhewing it ſelf in ſome unwarrantable practiſe, or other. So was it with the <hi>falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> and other <hi>falfe Teachers</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth them in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi> Thus ſpeaking of that pair of Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Hereticks, <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. he ſaith that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170416:33"/>
               <hi>having put away a good conſcience they made ſhipwrack of faith.</hi> Firſt they let looſe the reins to licentiouſneſſe, and then they made ſhipwrack of the doctrine of faith, being drowned in Errours and Hereſies. And truly ſo is it, where the latter of theſe is let go, the former is ſeldom retained. Falſe Teachers (pretend what they will) are ſeldom truly conſcientious. And ſo again, chap. 4. verſe 2. ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>ſeducing ſpirits,</hi> that ſhould come in the latter times, falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſpreading their Errours under a pretence of being inſpired by the ſpirit of God, he deſcribeth them to be ſuch as ſhould <hi>ſpeak lies in hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, having their conſciences ſeared with a hot iron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſcientiam habentes inu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtam notis cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum quibus quibus ſibi ſunt conſcii,</note> Putting on a vail of ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſanctity to cover their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hereſies with, but having <hi>bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſciences</hi> (as <hi>Grotius</hi> expounds it) being ſtigmatized with the marks of ſome foul and enormous crimes, which they indulge and allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in; like <hi>Rogues</hi> who are burnt in the hand or ſhoulder, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the body, whereby they may be known for ſuch as they are;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170416:34"/>Or <hi>conſciences cauterized</hi> (which word exactly anſwereth the word in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal, being derived from it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſeared, made inſenſible of their own dangerous condition, and of the righteous judgements of God, and ſo going on in ſome wicked courſe or other. And ſo fareth it oft-times with ſuch <hi>Teachers;</hi> They are no leſſe erroneous in their <hi>lives</hi> then <hi>Doctrines.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Some particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars inſtanced in.</note> To inſtance in ſome particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Falſe-teachers ordinarily proud.</note> Ordinarily they are <hi>proud:</hi> So the ſame Apoſtle deſcribeth thoſe ſame <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> chap. 6. verſe 3. of the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>If any man teach otherwiſe</hi> (ſaith he) &amp;c. <hi>He is proud,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, puffed up, ſwollen with a <hi>tympanie</hi> of ſpiritual pride. And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo is it; ſeldom ſhall we meet with a falſe Teacher but is ſick of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, ſwollen up with a high conceit of himſelf, of his own parts and gifts, which maketh him decline the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon road, finding out ſome new way, broaching ſome new Doctrine, that he may have the honour of the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo be thought to be <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body</hi> (as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaith of <hi>Theudas, Act.</hi> 5.36.)</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170416:34"/> 2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <note place="margin">Often cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous.</note> And as Proud ſo alſo oft-times <hi>Covetous.</hi> So it there followeth in the next verſe of that chapter, ver. 5. <hi>Suppoſing that gain is godlineſs.</hi> This do falſe teachers oft-times, they make this their laſt end, making their teaching an <hi>Art of lucre,</hi> and making the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which is the <hi>doctrine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> ſubſervient to thoſe baſe ends. So the ſame Apoſtle in his other Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſets them forth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1, 2. Where in the four or five firſt verſes, we have a large deſcription of them, many of their qualities pointed at, and this among the reſt, <hi>this know,</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>Timothy) that in the laſt dayes perillous times ſhall come,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hard, troubleſom, difficult and dangerous times, and that in regard of the ſpiritual ſtate of the Church,) <hi>for men ſhal be lovers of their own ſelves, covetous, boaſters, proud, blaſphemers,</hi> and ſo he goeth on, inſtancing in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe particulars, But who are they whom the Apoſtle thus brandeth? why the ſixth verſe will tell us; <hi>Of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women; Falſe teachers,</hi> who oftimes are juſtly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170416:35"/>with both theſe, of being <hi>proud</hi> and <hi>covetous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <note place="margin">Not ſeldome Luxurious.</note> Yea, and (in the third place) <hi>Luxurious.</hi> So Saint <hi>Peter</hi> deſcribeth them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. where foretelling the ſame that <hi>Paul</hi> there did, that there ſhould be <hi>falſe teachers</hi> in the Church which ſhould <hi>privily bring in damnable Hereſies,</hi> verſe 1. he ſheweth what ones they ſhould be; <hi>And many</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhall follow their pernitious wayes,</hi> verſe 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Exitia,</hi> their <hi>perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Beza Gr. Annot ad loc.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>deſtructions,</hi> or (as divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther copies read it) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Luxurias,</hi> (as the <hi>vulgar Latine</hi> renders it) their <hi>luxuries,</hi> their laſcivious wayes and courſes, which were pernitious ways. To which alſo in the next words hee joyns their <hi>covetouſneſs; And through covetouſneſs ſhall they with feigned words make merchandize of you, verſe</hi> 3. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a feigned kinde of ſpeech, framed to a ſhew of more then ordinary Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Charity, and Meekneſſe, they ſhall endeavour to lay hold of your eſtates with the ruine of your ſouls, (as <hi>Diodate</hi> explains it.) Such may falſe Teachers oft-times bee found, <hi>proud, covetous, luxurious.</hi> So they are
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170416:35"/>there ſet forth more fully, verſe 10. where he giveth this further Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter of thoſe whom he ſpake of; They are ſuch (ſaith he) <hi>as walked after the fleſh in the luſts of uncleanneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe government, preſumtuous are they, ſelf-willed, &amp;c.</hi> And again, verſe 14. <hi>Having eyes full of adultery, and that cannot ceaſe from ſin, beguiling unſtable ſouls; an heart they have exerciſed with covetous practiſes,</hi> &amp;c. Thus Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> with whom Saint <hi>Jude</hi> alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curs, deſcribing them after the very ſelf ſame manner, by the ſame Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, as we ſhall finde it, verſe 4. and 10. of his Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>And ſuch as they deſcribed them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vtrumque, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitioſum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp; prorſus corporis uolup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fuiſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrant ipſius errores. Danae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in</hi> Auguſt <hi>de</hi> Haereſ. cap. 8.</note> ſuch the after ages found them. Such was that forenamed <hi>Cerinthus,</hi> a moſt ambitious and voluptuous perſon, as (beſides the Records which are left of him) is juſtly collected from ſome of his <hi>Errours;</hi> in ſpecial that <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenarie</hi> opinion of his, the <hi>thouſand years reign</hi> of the Saints after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, wherein they ſhould (as he apprehended) enjoy all kinde of carnal and ſenſual pleaſures, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hee was the firſt broacher. And
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170416:36"/>ſuch were thoſe <hi>Nicolaitanes,</hi> whom the Greek <hi>Scholiaſt</hi> conceiveth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to have an eye at in that Text forecited, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.2. and whom our Evangeliſt Saint <hi>John</hi> maketh menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of by name, verſe 6. of this chap. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. they were an impure genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe deeds were deſervedly <hi>hated both of God and men.</hi> And of the ſame kinde were the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> whom ſome look upon as a branch of the ſame ſtock, the of-ſpring of thoſe <hi>Nicolaitanes</hi> (if not the ſame) A proud generation.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gnoſtici propter excellentiam ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae ſic ſe appellatos eſſe, vel appellari de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſe gloriantur eum ſint ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus omnibus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niores atque turpiores.</hi> Aug. <hi>de</hi> Haeres.</note> So much their very name which they gave to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves imports, <hi>Gnoſtici, Gnoſticks,</hi> ſo called <hi>propter excellentiam ſcientiae</hi> (as <hi>Augustin</hi> giveth the reaſon of it) for the eminency of their knowledge, wherein they thought themſelves to excel all others; But not more <hi>proud</hi> then <hi>vile,</hi> being given up to all kinde of filthineſſe; from whence they had another name given them, which far better agreed to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then the former, being called <hi>Borboritae, quaſi coenoſi</hi> (as the ſame father interprets it) ſc. <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter nimiam turpitudinem,</hi> for their wallowing like ſwine in the mire of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170416:36"/>all kinde of filthineſſe, (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> alſo deſcribeth ſome of the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> of his time, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. laſt, where wee have that word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.) And ſuch were divers others of thoſe ancient Hereticks in, and near unto thoſe primitive times, as the writings of the Fathers ſet them forth; ſuch as whoſe lives did ſufficiently proclaim them to be what in truth they were, nothing leſſe then what they gave out themſelves to be. And I might ſhew the like in ſome of the ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Sects and Hereſies of latter times. But I ſuppoſe even your own obſervation and experience may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh you with but too many inſtances in this kinde, of men pretending to more light then others, who thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have taken upon them to mint new doctrines, and to lay out new wayes, yet their practiſes have plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewn that they were out of Gods way, walking in darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proceed no further. You ſee how, and in what way ſuch <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> as theſe in the Text are to be try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. What then remains but that, as
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170416:37"/>occaſion is offered, meeting with ſuch <hi>teachers,</hi> you put them upon the try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, trying them by their <hi>Calling, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Life;</hi> which doing, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you ſhall finde what the <hi>angel</hi> of this Church is here ſaid to have done, you ſhall <hi>find them Lyars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Part. </seg>2</label> And ſo I am fallen upon the ſecond part of the Text,
<note place="margin">The iſſue of this trial.</note> wherein wee have the <hi>Iſſue</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of this underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. The <hi>angel</hi> of this Church ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king tryal of theſe pretended <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> he found them <hi>lyars.</hi> Of which very briefly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lyars]</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">Falſe apoſtles called lyars. <hi>Perkins</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition in Text.</note> a broad and a foul word, yet not found fault with, but approved by Chriſt, being here given to theſe <hi>Falſe Apoſtles.</hi> From whence Mr. <hi>Perkins</hi> obſerves not amiſſe; that</p>
            <p>Though Railing and taunting can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not beſeem any,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> Broad Language wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantably given by Magiſtrates and miniſters to ſome offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> yet <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> in their places may give out <hi>ſevere ſpeeches</hi> againſt offenders, in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of deteſtation of their ſins, and not offend. For this he inſtanceth in <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who called the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, a Generation of Vipers,</hi> Mat. 3.6. And ſo in our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170416:37"/>who called <hi>Herod a Fox, Luke</hi> 13.32. And in <hi>Paul,</hi> who writing to his back-ſliding <hi>Galathians,</hi> puts the <hi>Fool</hi> upon them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. And ſo the ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> having to deal with <hi>Elimas</hi> the ſorcerer, a great and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſeducer, he <hi>being filled with the Holy Ghoſt</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>ſet his eyes upon him, and ſaid, O full of all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty and miſchief, thou childe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Act. 3.9, 10. And thus it is here ſaid of this <hi>Angel,</hi> (the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> or <hi>Miniſters</hi> of this Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi>) having try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe falſe Apoſtles, he <hi>found them Lyars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Found lyars, how.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Found them]</hi> Even as an <hi>Inqueſt</hi> or <hi>Iury</hi> that paſſeth upon a <hi>Malefactor,</hi> is ſaid to <hi>find him guilty,</hi> judging and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring him ſo. So did this <hi>Angel</hi> here <hi>finde</hi> theſe <hi>Falſe Apostles;</hi> having brought them to the tryall, upon good evidence he found them <hi>Lyars,</hi> judging and pronouncing them ſo to be. So the Prophets both <hi>Iſay</hi> and <hi>Jeremie</hi> call thoſe <hi>Wizards</hi> and <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> who in their predictions promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a long continuance, and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170416:38"/>ſtate to the <hi>Babylonian Monarchy. That frustrateth the tokens of the Lyars,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iſay</hi> chapter 44.25.) <hi>A ſword is upon the Lyars</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jeremy,</hi> chapter 50.36.) And ſuch this <hi>Angel</hi> here found theſe falſe Apoſtles, <hi>Lyars;</hi> ſuch as not onely ſpake that which was <hi>falſe</hi> in it ſelf, but ſpake it knowingly with a minde to deceive.</p>
            <p>Such properly are <hi>Lyars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lyars proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly who.</note> Not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that ſpeaketh an untruth, which true and honeſt men may doe unawares, unwittingly, againſt their wills, who thereupon do not deſerve this <hi>brand,</hi> to bee called <hi>Lyars.</hi> But when any ſhall do it knowingly and willingly, <hi>animo fallendi,</hi> with a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to deceive. So did theſe <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> here in the Text, <hi>They ſaid they were Apoſtles,</hi> which they were not, and which they knew they were not; and they did it purpoſely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people, thereby to inſinuate themſelves into their affections, to gain reſpect to their perſons, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to their falſe doctrines, which they held forth.
<note place="margin">Lying a foul crime.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>A foul crime;</hi> Such is <hi>Lying.</hi> So
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170416:38"/>the <hi>ſpirit of God</hi> looked upon it, whilſt it reckoneth thoſe who are habitual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cuſtomarily ſuch, among that curſed crew, thoſe <hi>abominable</hi> ones; <hi>Murtherers, Whoremongers, Sorcerers, Idolaters, and all Lyars,</hi> ſo you have them put together, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. and 22.15. and the ſame doom paſſed upon them as upon the other, <hi>viz.</hi> that they ſhall <hi>have their part in the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which (not to dwell upon it) let it make all who hear it wary;
<note place="margin">Aplication. Take heed of it.</note> leſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tryal they ſhould be found in this number, <hi>Lyars</hi> in any kinde. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe kindes of <hi>Lyars,</hi> and <hi>Lying</hi> we meet with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Scripture.
<note place="margin">Three kinds of Lyes. and Lying.</note> Three moſt obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. There is a <hi>Civil Lye;</hi> ſuch as is uſed too often in bargaining,
<note place="margin">A civil Lye.</note> in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts; and other affairs of this life; which ſome diſtinguiſh into a <hi>Jocoſe,</hi> and a <hi>ſerious</hi> Lye, a <hi>merry,</hi> and a <hi>very</hi> Lye, a Lye in <hi>Jeſt,</hi> and a Lye in <hi>earneſt;</hi> The latter of which they ſub-divide into a <hi>Noxious</hi> and <hi>Officious</hi> Lye; which laſt they give allowance to.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170416:39"/>An <hi>officious Lye;</hi> which is made in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of others, for their help or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit. But even this <hi>Lye,</hi> however it hath a <hi>mask</hi> put upon the face of it, carrying a ſhew of honeſty and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<note place="margin">An officious Lye not to be allowed.</note> becauſe it is beneficiall to our neighbour, without any wrong or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment (it may be) to any, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed and in truth it is no more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable then the former: Being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Commandment</hi> of God, which forbiddeth a <hi>lie</hi> to be told in what cafe ſoever. Surely if a man may not <hi>tell a lye, or talk deceitfully for God</hi> (which <hi>Job</hi> ſharply reproves in his friends, <hi>Job</hi> 13.7.) much leſs then may he tell a Lye for his <hi>neighbour. Truth</hi> is a precious this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weighing down what ever can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ballance againſt it. Whereupon the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> forbiddeth to part with it, upon any termes. <hi>Buy the truth, but ſell it not, Prov.</hi> 23.23. O take heed Chriſtians! that none of you who profeſſe your ſelves to be <hi>of the truth,</hi> (as Saint <hi>John</hi> ſpeaketh of ſincere Chriſtians, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.19.) the true children of that <hi>God</hi> who is <hi>the God of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170416:39"/>truth,</hi> the true diſciples of Chriſt, who ſtiles himſelf the <hi>Truth, John</hi> 14.6. be found <hi>lyars</hi> in this kinde. Knowing that you muſt be <hi>tryed;</hi> though hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily not by man here, whom you may deceive, yet by <hi>God</hi> hereafter, who cannot be deceived. Whoſe <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> being <hi>according to truth</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2.) he will certainly then find out thoſe that are <hi>Lyars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. There is an <hi>Hypocritical lye.</hi>
               <note place="margin">An hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal lye.</note> A counrerfeit profeſſion of Religion; when men have onely that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that outward <hi>form of godlineſs</hi> (as the Apoſtle calleth it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.) When <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance</hi> and other Graces are diſſembled. Of this <hi>lying</hi> ſpeaketh Saint <hi>John,</hi> 1 Epiſt. 1.6. <hi>If we ſay that we have fellowſhip with him,</hi> and walk in darkneſſe, (profeſſe uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and communion with God and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and yet go on in ſinfull wayes and courſes) <hi>we lye.</hi> Such <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> were <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas, Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira.</hi> Such were the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> whom our Saviour fitly compares to <hi>painted Tombs,</hi> upon this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170416:40"/>account denouncing a <hi>woe</hi> againſt them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.27, 28. <hi>Woe unto you Scribes and Phariſees Hypocrites, for ye are like unto whited ſepulchres, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are beautiful outwardly, but within are full of dead mens bones, and all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe. Even ſo ye outwardly appear righteous unto men, but within ye are full of hypocriſie and iniquity.</hi> And ſuch are all <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> who profeſſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be what they are not, having fair faces, but foul hearts, <hi>lyars</hi> all. Now take heed again that none of you be found in this number, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and remembring that there will come a day of <hi>Tryal.</hi> Such ſhall that laſt day be; when <hi>all muſt appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive according to that which they have done in the body, whether it bee good or evil,</hi> (as the Apoſtle tells us in the ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the fifth chapter, verſe 10.) Now that day will bee <hi>a day of Revelation,</hi> the <hi>Revelation of the righteous judgement of God</hi> (as the ſame Apoſtle calls it in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> chapter 2. verſe 5.) Then ſhall all maſkes
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170416:40"/>and diſguizes bee pulled off, and all ſhall appear to bee what in truth they were; All ſtanding naked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunal of Jeſus Chriſt. O take heed that none of you then bee found <hi>Lyars!</hi> Which if you ſhall bee, O what ſhame and confuſion will then cover your faces? Then muſt you look for no other but the <hi>Lyars portion,</hi> to bee <hi>ſhut out with Dogs</hi> (as the Text hath it in the <hi>Revelations</hi> chapter 22. verſe 15.) to have your part in that Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, There is an <hi>Heretical Lye,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An heretical Lye.</note> a falſhood in matter of Chriſtian <hi>Doctrine;</hi> when ſome Doctrine is held forth contrary to the Word. Of this <hi>lye</hi> ſpeaketh Saint <hi>John</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, chapter 2. verſe 21. <hi>No lye is of the Truth;</hi> calling the <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> or <hi>maintainers</hi> thereof, <hi>Lyars. Who is a lyar, but he that denieth that Jeſus is the Chriſt</hi> (ſo it followeth in verſe 22.) Now take heed alſo that none of you be found amongſt theſe <hi>lyars.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſe Lyars to bee avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note>
            </p>
            <p>To which end <hi>avoid thoſe that are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170416:41"/>ſo, and found to bee ſo.</hi> This will men do by thoſe who are found to be <hi>Cheaters,</hi> ſetting forth falſe wares to ſale, or minting of falſe and counterfeit Coyn, not of the right ſtamp or mettal, all will take heed of them, no man will truſt them. And ſo deal you by <hi>Falſe Teachers.</hi> Many of which of late times have been <hi>Tryed by the Angels of the Churches,</hi> the true and faithfull <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt in this Nation, (whom (as I ſaid) Chriſt hath made <hi>Tryers by Office</hi>) and they have been found by them <hi>lyars,</hi> (ſo declared and proved by their Preaching and Writing) no better then <hi>Cheaters,</hi> holding forth falſe, dangerous and pernitious Doctrines. As you love your ſouls, take heed of them, truſt them not, <hi>Avoid them.</hi> That is <hi>Pauls</hi> earneſt obteſtation to his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> (as before you heard) in that his Epiſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. verſe 17. And let it now be mine to you, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as a cloſure to what I ſhall ſay upon this Text and this ſubject. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, mark them which
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170416:41"/>cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to</hi> (or <hi>beſides,</hi> for that ſenſe the word will well bear; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doctrinam</hi> (as the vulgar Latine renders it) <hi>beſides) the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhun all voluntary and intimate ſociety with them.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoc argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum facitut cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam non fuiſſe tunc conventus communes aut Presbyterium Romae Alioqui voluiſſet tales excommunicari.</hi> Grot. Annot. in loc.</note> This (as <hi>Grotius</hi> conceives of it) was all that thoſe beleeving <hi>Romanes</hi> were then in a capacity of doing, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as yet formed into an <hi>Original Church,</hi> ſo as to have any <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or any <hi>Church Government</hi> among them; which had they had, ſurely (ſaith hee) <hi>Paul</hi> would have given them ſome other directions, willed them to have dealt otherwiſe by them: <hi>viz.</hi> to have <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> them, according as they deſerved. But however it was with them, ſure wee are (what we have juſt cauſe to lament and complain of to God and man) ſo it is generally with the Churches of Chriſt in this Nation at this day,
<note place="margin">The onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy in theſe looſe times.</note> which have no <hi>Government</hi> ſet up among them, no authorized <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> onely acting, what any
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170416:42"/>of them do, in a precarious way; by reaſon whereof thoſe <hi>Falſe Teachers</hi> which abound every where, cannot bee proceeded againſt, as otherwiſe they ſhould bee, in a publick way, ſtruck with the <hi>thunder-bolt of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication,</hi> and <hi>delivered to Satan</hi> (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith hee dealt by <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> chapter 1. and the laſt verſe) <hi>that they might learn not to blaſpheme:</hi> What then remaines, but that in a <hi>private way</hi> they bee ſhunned and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>biſine tali re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regimine eſt ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia nihil a i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ud poſſunt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li quam declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re familiarem convictum cum iis qui non ex regulâ Chriſti vivunt</hi> Grot. <hi>ubi ſupra.</hi>
               </note> And this let me leave with you; Shall ſuch come amongſt you? own them not, receive them not, not into your houſes. For this, that of this our Evangeliſt Saint <hi>Iohu</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe in that forecited Text, in his ſecond Epiſtle, chapter 10. <hi>If there come any unto you, and bring not this Doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, neither bid him God ſpeed.</hi> To which hee ſubjoyneth an Argument or Reaſon in the next words; <hi>For he that biddeth him God ſpeed, is partaker of his evil deeds,</hi> verſe 11. And if you may not <hi>receive them into your
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170416:42"/>houſes;</hi> ſurely by a Parity of Reaſon, you may not go to theirs, not repair to their <hi>meetings,</hi> which how pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous it hath proved to ſome, and not a few, of late times, I ſhall not need to tell you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But it will be ſaid, What?
<note place="margin">Chriſtians not to frequent the meetings of falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, nor to be familiar with them.</note> have nothing to do with them? how then ſhall wee <hi>try</hi> them? If wee may not go to <hi>their houſes,</hi> to their <hi>meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall we try their <hi>Doctrines?</hi> And if wee may not receive them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>our houſes,</hi> ſo as to converſe and be familiar with them, how ſhall we try their <hi>Practiſe,</hi> their Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vertigo,</hi> or The turning ſicknes of ſoul unſetledneſſe. Printed 1655. The falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tryed and diſcovered, Printed 1656.</note> To this I ſuppoſe you now expect that I ſhould return an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; but having my ſelf heretofore done it in this place, treating upon that Text in the thirteenth chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> verſe 9. and finding it again ſince done by that <hi>Reverend Brother</hi> fore-mentioned in his Treatiſe upon this Text which I have now handled; both which I preſume are, or may bee in your hands, I ſhall now forbear that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170416:43"/>commending what hath been ſpoken to your practiſe; and your ſelves to him who is of <hi>power to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh you; to whom be Honour and glory now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
